<!--
  The contents of this file are subject to the University of Utah Public
  License (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.
  
  Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the
  License for the specific language governing rights and limitations under
  the License.
  
  The Original Source Code is SCIRun, released March 12, 2001.
  
  The Original Source Code was developed by the University of Utah.
  Portions created by UNIVERSITY are Copyright (C) 2001, 1994 
  University of Utah. All Rights Reserved.
-->

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE dir SYSTEM "../../../doc/UserGuide/dirspec.dtd">

<dir name="Core/Exceptions">
  <fit>
  <!-- describe how this directory fits into SCIRun - why does it 
       exist, how does SCIRun benefit from it, etc. -->
    <p>
       The Exceptions directory contains common exceptions and the Exception
       base class.  Developers can create new exception classes, and these
       will need to be in other directories if they depend on other data
       structures outside of the Exception dir.
    </p>

    <p>
       All exceptions in SCIRun are derived from the SCIRun::Exception
       base class.  All derived classes implement a message method and a
       type method.   The type method just returns a string (const char*
       actually) that indicates the classname of the exception.  The message
       returns a human readable string that can be printed out when the
       exception is caught.
    </p>

    <p>
       This directory also contains some general exceptions used throughout 
       SCIRun. 
       AssertionFailed - thrown when an assertion fails.
       ArrayIndexOutOfBounds - thrown to indicate a failed bounds check.
       DimensionMismatch - thrown to indicate dimensionality differences.
       FileNotFound - thrown when a file is not found.
       InternalError - thrown when an internal error occurs.
    </p>
  </fit>
  <use>
    <why>
    <!-- Discuss why a developer would need or want to use the
         functions and/or classes in this directory. -->
      <p>
        Exceptions are the preffered method of error handling in SCIRun.
        A developer is likely to use this code in two possible ways.  One is
        to use a predefined exception that we provide here in this directory.
        The other is to inherit from Exception to create a new exception 
        specific to the developers code.
      </p>
    </why>
    <when>
    <!-- Discuss when or where to use the functions and classes in
         this directory: From within modules?, when a certain event
	 occurs? -->
      <p>
        A developer is likely to use this code from within written modules 
        as well as within new datatypes. Anywhere that flexible error 
        handling is preffered.
      </p>

      <p>
         A couple development specific hints follow. 
      </p> 
      <p>
         All exception classes must implement a copy constructor (for some
         compilers).
      </p>
      <p>
         On the SGI, the exception classes will give you a stacktrace when
         they are caught (uses -lexc).
      </p>
    </when>
  </use
</dir>

<!-- author comments: suggestions for new/better tags for this xml file

  I think this file should address known bugs, i.e. have a <bugs> tag.

-->