<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE component SYSTEM "../../../doc/Utilities/XML/component.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../doc/Utilities/XML/component.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?cocoon-process type="xslt"?>

<!--
  The contents of this file are subject to the University of Utah Public
  License (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.
  
  Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the
  License for the specific language governing rights and limitations under
  the License.
  
  The Original Source Code is SCIRun, released March 12, 2001.
  
  The Original Source Code was developed by the University of Utah.
  Portions created by UNIVERSITY are Copyright (C) 2001, 1994 
  University of Utah. All Rights Reserved.
-->


<component name="Isosurface" category="Visualization">
  <overview>
    <authors>
      <author>Yarden Livnat</author>
    </authors>
    <summary>Isosurface allows visualization of an isopotential
     surface within a model. IsoSurface also allows interactive extraction of isosurfaces in the voltage field.  
     </summary>
     <description>
      <p>A small sphere controls the starting point of the isosurface alogorithm, and an attached 3D arrow widget may be moved using the mouse, allowing interactive exploration of the voltage field.  Dragging on the arrow allows the the user to move the widget along the line defined by the gradient; dragging on the sphere allows unconstrained movement of the seed point.</p>

<p>In the Isosurface module GUI, changing the Iso Value allows visualization of any isopotential surface. The Update options are: On Release, Manual and Auto.  On Release will not re-execute the module until the user releases the Iso Value scroll bar. If the user selects the Manual option, the module will not re-execute until they press the Extract button.  The Auto option re-executes the module every time the Iso Value scroll bar moves. If the user selects the Auto Extract from New Field option and a new Field comes in, the module completely re-executes, calculating a new Isosurface.  The Build TriSurfField check box allows the user to pass the generated Isosurface downstream. If the ColorMap does not pass in to the Isosurface module, the user can specify the Default Color. </p>
      <p>The Isosurface can be calculated using the Marching Cubes method (MC), which examines the isopotential at the
      corners of every cell.  For this method, the user can specify the number of Threads
     .</p>
      <p> The Noise method stores the minimum and maximum values of all cells into a
      table.
      </p>
      <p>The Isosurface module is used to visualize surfaces or lines
        of constant value within a scalar field.  The Iso Value slider in the GUI determines which value is used to generate the
        isopotential surface.  The Update options are: On Release,
        Manual and Auto.  On Release will not re-execute the
        module until the user releases the Iso Value scroll bar. If
        manual is selected, the module will not re-execute until the
	Extract button is pressed.  The Auto option re-executes the modul eevery time the Iso Value scroll bar moves. If the user selects the Auto Extract from New Field option and a new Field comes in, the
	module completely re-executes, calculating a new Isosurface.  The Build Output Field check box allows the user to pass the generated Isosurface downstream as a field. If there is no ColorMap passed in to the module, the user can specify the Default Color to
        use instead.</p>
      <p> The Isosurface can be calculated using the Marching Cubes
method, which examines the isopotential at the corners of every
element within the input field.  This operation may be parallelized, and allows the user to specify how many threads are used to do the
computation.  This is a good choice if examining only a few isovalues.      </p>
      <p>
	The NOISE method computes and stores a table containing all of the input field elements and their values.  Then when the isovalue is specified the surface can be extracted more quickly by looking in the table for the appropriate values.  This gives better interactive
performance at the cost of some setup time and space.  
      </p>
      <p>
        As of September 2002, this module can manage scalar fields of the following geometry type: LatVolField, StructHexVolField, TetVolField,HexVolField, TriSurfField, QuadSurfField and ImageField.
Isocontours are generated for the surface input fields, and
Isosurfaces are generated for the volume input fields.
      </p>
      <p>
        As of Febuary 2003, this module can handle scalar fields that
        contain cell-centered data.  If the data is located at the
        cells, then the surfaces are created along the appropriate
        cell faces rather than using interpolated values from the
        nodes.
      </p>
    </description>
  </overview>
  <io>
    <inputs lastportdynamic="no">
      <port>
        <name>Field</name>
	<datatype>SCIRun::Field</datatype>
      </port>
      <port>
        <name>Optional Color Map</name>
	<datatype>SCIRun::ColorMap</datatype>
      </port>
      <port>
        <name>Optional Isovalues</name>
	<datatype>SCIRun::Matrix</datatype>
      </port>
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
      <port>
        <name>Surface</name>
	<datatype>SCIRun::Field</datatype>
      </port>
      <port>
        <name>Geometry</name>
	<datatype>SCIRun::Geometry</datatype>
      </port>
    </outputs>
  </io>
  <gui>
    <img>../Modules/Visualization/doc/IsoSurfaceUI.jpg</img>
  </gui>
  <testing>
  </testing>
</component> 










