<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE component SYSTEM "../../../doc/Utilities/XML/component.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../doc/Utilities/XML/component.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?cocoon-process type="xslt"?>

<!--
  The contents of this file are subject to the University of Utah Public
  License (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.
  
  Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the
  License for the specific language governing rights and limitations under
  the License.
  
  The Original Source Code is SCIRun, released March 12, 2001.
  
  The Original Source Code was developed by the University of Utah.
  Portions created by UNIVERSITY are Copyright (C) 2001, 1994 
  University of Utah. All Rights Reserved.
-->


<component name="SampleStructHex" category="Fields">
  <overview>
    <authors>
      <author>Michael Callahan</author>
    </authors>
    <summary>
      Make a StructHexVolField that fits the source field.
    </summary>
    <description>

      <p> Make a StructHexVolField that fits the source field.  The
      value type of the LatVolField is the same as that of the input
      field.  If there is no input field specified, then create a unit
      volume of doubles.  The size parameters refer to the number of
      nodes in the volume, not the number of cells.  Thus a 2x2x2 node
      lattice will only contain one cell. </p>

      <p> The Pad Percentage parameter is an optional parameter that
      describes how much larger than the input field the resulting
      lattice volume should be.  For example, a value of 100 would
      make the lattice volume be three times as far across and contain
      twenty seven times the volume of a lattice with the default 0
      padding.  A value of 50 would cause the lattice to be twice as
      far across (50% bigger on each side).  </p>

      <p> No interpolation is done onto the new field.  It is
      recommended that the DirectInterpolate module be used if those
      values are needed. </p>

      <p> The default appearance of this field is not much different than that
      produced by the SampleLattice.  However the points can be moved
      independently of each other such that primitive modeling can be
      done in conjunction with the ManageFieldMesh module.  See the
      SampleStructHex.net sample network for an example. </p>

    </description>
  </overview>
  <io>
    <inputs lastportdynamic="no">
      <port>
	<name>Input Field</name>
	<datatype>SCIRun::Field</datatype>
      </port>
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
      <port>
	<name>Output Sample Field</name>
	<datatype>SCIRun::Field</datatype>
      </port>
    </outputs>
  </io>
  <testing>
  </testing>
</component>
