<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE component SYSTEM "../../../doc/ReferenceGuide/component.dtd">
<component name="ShowGeometry" category="Fields">
  <overview>
    <authors>
      <author>Martin J. Cole</author>
    </authors>
    <summary>Module to visualize the mesh inside a field.</summary>
    <description>
      <p>The ShowGeometry module is useful to verify a fields mesh. If you read in a field, but are not sure how it is organized this module will help you visualize it. The display is somewhat customizeable through its user interface.</p>
      <developer>
	<p>This module tries to handle any field type that is input. It draws spheres or a node local axis at its verticies. Connectivity is shown as thin lines connecting the verticies.  Colors for each are customizable in the user interface.</p>
	<p>The size that spheres or axes are draw is 20 percent of a cell. Perhaps this should be another user control in the gui.</p>
      </developer>
    </description>
    <examplesr></examplesr>
  </overview>
  <io>
    <inputs>
      <!-- one of (device port file) -->
      <port>
	<description>
	  <p> The one and only input port.  ShowGeometry handles any type of field as input.</p>
	</description>
	<datatype>SField</datatype>
	<componentname>ReadField</componentname>
      </port>
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
      <!-- one of (device port file) -->
      <port>
	<description>
          <p> The one and only output port.  ShowGeometry outputs geometry, that represents the mesh inside the input field.
          </p>
	</description>
	<datatype>GeomGroup</datatype>
	<componentname>Salmon</componentname>
      </port>
    </outputs>
  </io>
  <gui>
    <description>
      <p> The ShowGeometry dialog contains all the user configurable elements of visualizing the mesh. It is divided into two main sections, on the left is a frame that holds Node Display Options, on the right is a frame that holds the Connection Display Options. Along the bottom are the Execute and Dismiss buttons.
      </p>
    </description>
    <parameter>
      <label>Node Display Type</label>
      <description>
	<p>These are the node rendering options. Only one option may be active at a time. Currently the user can change selection, then must also hit the execute button to see the results visually within the rendering window. Options are: render as Spheres (the default) or render as Axes.</p>
      </description>
    </parameter>
    <parameter>
      <label>Set Color (within Node Display Options frame)</label>
      <description>
	<p>Set color will pop up the color selection widget. After selecting the desired color the color swatch to the right of the Set Color button will reflect the selected color, and the color that nodes are displayed will change within the rendering window as well. No execute call is needed.</p>
      </description>
    </parameter>
    <parameter>
      <label>Show Connections</label>
      <description>
	<p>This check button allows the user to toggle between displaying and not displaying connections in the rendering window.</p>
      </description>
    </parameter>
    <parameter>
      <label>Set Color (within Connection Display Options frame)</label>
      <description>
	<p>Set color will pop up the color selection widget. After selecting the desired color the color swatch to the right of the Set Color button will reflect the selected color, and the color that connections are displayed will change within the rendering window as well. No execute call is needed.</p>
      </description>
    </parameter>
    <parameter>
      <label>Execute</label>
      <description>
	<p>Selecting this button causes the module to execute.</p>
      </description>
    </parameter>
    <parameter>
      <label>Dismiss</label>
      <description>
	<p>Selecting this button will cause the dialog to close.</p>
      </description>
    </parameter>
    <img>./doc/ShowGeometryGUI.gif</img>
  </gui>
  <testing>
    <plan>
      <description>
      </description>
      <steps>
	<step></step>
      </steps>
    </plan>
  </testing>
</component>

