<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE dir SYSTEM "../../../doc/UserGuide/dirspec.dtd">
 
<dir name="Core/TkExtensions">

<!-- ************** phase 1 content ************** -->
 
  <fit>
  <!-- describe how this directory fits into SCIRun - why does it
       exist, how does SCIRun benefit from it, etc. -->
    <p>
      
      The main purpose of this directory is provide additional GUI
      componenet that are needed by SCIRun but are not provided by
      Tk nor are easily implemented (if at all) in native TclTk. 
      These extensions include support for an OpenGL window, three 
      dimension look and feel and moving the cursor to a specified
      window. These extensions are implemented here in C++ and are
      added to the Tk built in commands in the initialization stage.
    </p>
  </fit>
 
  <use>
    <why>
    <!-- Discuss why a developer would need or want to use the
         functions and/or classes in this directory. -->
      <p>
	There are three componenets to this interface: Initialization,
	extensions and a hack of the Tk internals. GUI extensions to Tk
	should be implemented here and added to the Tk built in commands
	via the initialization in tkAppInit.c

	A special attention should be given to the tclUnixNotify-*.c 
	files. These files are a hack of a similar file internal to Tk.
	Their purpose is to enable Tk to work in a multithreaded 
	environment even though it was not designed to do so. Since the
	coresponding file in the Tk distribution changes between different
	versions of Tk we have included a modified version for the two
	versions of Tk that are supported by SCIRun, namely 8.0.4 and 8.3 .
      </p>
    </why>

    <when>
    <!-- Discuss when or where to use the functions and classes in
         this directory: From within modules?, when a certain event
	 occurs? -->
      <p>
        The code in this directory is meant to be used only via the tcl 
	commands that it provides. Any tcl code can call these commands
	to create the GUI they provide.
      </p>
    </when>
  </use>

<!-- ************** phase 2 content ************** -->

  <definition>
  <!-- Give the definition for a term, or concept, that is embodied
       by this directory.  Please provide feature length rather than
       short story definitions. -->
    <term>
      tk command
    </term>
    <p>
      Tk provides a set of builtin GUI commands. One can augement them
      by providing additional functions writen in C++ (or C). These 
      additional functions can interface the TCL/TK system via C function
      calls as describe in the TCL/TK documentation.
    </p>
  </definition>

  <definition>
  <!-- Give the definition for a term, or concept, that is embodied
       by this directory.  Please provide feature length rather than
       short story definitions. -->
    <term>
      tkOpenGL
    </term>
    <p>
      A Tk window that embodies an OpenGL window.
    </p>
  </definition>

  <example>
  <!-- give an example of how to use the classes and/or functions
       here.  Again, more is better, however give only exactly 
       that which is being explained, no superfluous text (i.e.
       please don't cut and paste from existing code.) -->
    
    <p>
    </p>
  </example>
</dir>

<!-- author comments: suggestions for new/better tags for this xml file



-->