<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE component SYSTEM "component.dtd">
<!--
   For more information, please see: http://software.sci.utah.edu

   The MIT License

   Copyright (c) 2004 Scientific Computing and Imaging Institute,
   University of Utah.

   License for the specific language governing rights and limitations under
   Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
   copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
   to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
   the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
   and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
   Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

   The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included
   in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

   THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS
   OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
   FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
   THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
   LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
   FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
   DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
-->

<?xml-stylesheet href="component.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?cocoon-process type="xslt"?>

<component name="SynchronizeGeometry" category="Render">
  <overview>
    <authors>
	<author>Kai Li</author>
    </authors>
    <summary>Create a barrier to synchronize a set of geometry streams.</summary>
    <description>
        <p> Unlike the other modules in SCIRun, the Viewer module is
	    asynchronous.  That is, ViewWindows redraw as soon as any
	    Geometry is added (or deleted) through any Viewer port.
	    This is typically the desired behavior, as it keeps the
	    visualizations optimally interactive.  However, this is
	    not desirable when creating animations, since a new
	    animation frame is generated each time there is a redraw.
	    On the contrary, when creating animations, users typically
	    want only a single redraw per time-step, and that redraw
	    should occur only when all of the scene geometry has been
	    updated.  The SynchronizeGeoemtry module provides
	    precisely this mechanism.  All of the Geometry that the
	    user wishes to change synchronously with each frame of the
	    animation (e.g. updated isosurfaces, streamlines,
	    psuedo-colored surface potential maps, etc) are passed
	    through the SynchronizeGeometry module before being passed
	    into the Viewer.  As updated Geometries are sent to
	    SynchronizeGeometry, it stores them in a buffer until all
	    of the inputs have been received; it then sends them to
	    the Viewer as a single atomic group, which results in a
	    single redraw event (and thus a single new frame for the
	    animation).
	</p>
	<p> A geometry stream is composed of multiple geometry samples.
	    Each geometry sample is created by calling GeometryOPort::
	    delObj() and/or GeometryOPort::addObj() one or more times.
	    All geometry samples with the same virtual sequence number
	    in differenct streams must reach the barrier before they can
	    all proceed. The boundary of geometry samples is the 
	    GeometryFlush or GeometryFlushViews message, which is sent 
	    out explicitly by calling functions like GeometryOPort::
	    flushViews(), or implicitly by SCIRun after you did some 
	    geometry operations (delete or add) in Module::execute() but 
	    did not call any flush messages. With a checkbox in the control
	    panel, users can dynamically choose whether or not to enforce 
	    the barrier.
	</p>
    </description>
  </overview>
  <implementation>
  </implementation>
  <io>
    <inputs lastportdynamic="yes">
      <port>
        <name>Input Geometry</name>
        <datatype>SCIRun::Geometry</datatype>
      </port>
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
      <port>
        <name>Output Geometry</name>
        <datatype>SCIRun::Geometry</datatype>
	<componentname>Viewer</componentname>
      </port>
    </outputs>
  </io>
  <gui>
    <parameter>
      <widget>Label</widget>
      <label>Autogenerated GUI explanation</label>
    </parameter>
  </gui>
  <testing>
  </testing>
</component>

